<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: nodejs | ChatStorm - DevBlog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.chatstorm.de/blog/categories/nodejs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.chatstorm.de/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-17T21:59:35+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.chatstorm.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Schindler]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[how to translate your expressjs app pages]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.chatstorm.de/blog/2013/09/17/how-to-translate-your-expressjs-app-pages/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T19:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.chatstorm.de/blog/2013/09/17/how-to-translate-your-expressjs-app-pages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>intro</h1>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<ul>
<li>there isn&rsquo;t the one and only best solution to translate your app in nodejs</li>
</ul>


<h3>long version</h3>

<p>In that post I will show one aproach of translating content in an expressjs app
as we do so in <a href="https://chatstorm.de.">https://chatstorm.de.</a> There are different approaches to
implement translations and all of them have their up and down sides. When I
looked around to find a practical way to translate nodejs apps, I realized that
nodejs and its libraries is still a very young technology where a lot of
problems are not solved yet. Many cool people implemented their own prototypes
of translations, but none of them really grew up until now. That is why I
decided to create my own appoach.  Here we go.</p>

<h1>my way</h1>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<ul>
<li>stupid simple</li>
<li>check preferred browser language based on request</li>
<li>set information of preferred language in view</li>
<li>serve all content for all languages</li>
<li>hide all content of all languages by default</li>
<li>only show that content matching the preferred language</li>
</ul>


<h3>long version</h3>

<p>The first thing we need to do is to get the information of the language the
view has to use. I used a package called
<a href="https://github.com/jed/locale">locale</a>.</p>

<p>Below is described how to install it.
<code>bash
npm install locale
</code></p>

<p>Below is described how to use it.
```coffeescript
Locale  = require &ldquo;locale&rdquo;
Express = require &ldquo;express&rdquo;</p>

<p>supportedLanguages = [ &ldquo;en&rdquo;, &ldquo;en_US&rdquo;, &ldquo;en-US&rdquo;, &ldquo;de&rdquo;, &ldquo;de_DE&rdquo;, &ldquo;de-DE&rdquo; ]</p>

<p>Express.use Locale(supportedLanguages)
```</p>

<p>In that way there will be a request property available you can pass to your
view.
```coffeescript
locals        = {}
locals.locale = req.locale</p>

<p>res.render &ldquo;view_name&rdquo;, locals
```</p>

<p>In our view we set the language information as class attribute of an HTML
element as described below. Here is shown a piece of jade snippet, where
we create an HTML element inside the body element, having the ID <code>page</code>
and the class <code>locale</code>, that contains the language information.</p>

<p>Having the language information present in our views, we are able to show the
matching translations. Below we see two heading elements having different
classes describing the translated language. All elements having the class
<code>tr-en</code> or <code>tr-de</code> will be hidden by default. Related to the language
information we have already set, we can show the element matching the language.</p>

<p>Here we see the css.
```css
.tr-en, .tr-de {
  display: none;
}</p>

<p>.en .tr-en,
.en_US .tr-en,
.en-US .tr-en,
.de .tr-de,
.de_DE .tr-de,
.de-DE .tr-de {
  display: inline-block;
}
```</p>

<p>Here we see the jade view.
```jade
body
  #page(class=locale)</p>

<pre><code>h1.tr-en Here is my english content
h1.tr-de Das hier ist mein deutscher Inhalt
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h1>summary</h1>

<h3>TL;DR</h3>

<ul>
<li>+ stupid simple</li>
<li>- deliver all content, even if we don&rsquo;t need it</li>
</ul>


<h3>long version</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s it. Here we have a very simple solution to translate content of our
expressjs app. It is simpler than everything else I found on the web and I am
fine with that. The only thing that is not that beautifull is, that we need
to deliver all content of all translations, even if we don&rsquo;t want to show it.
Further you could think about making the user be able to select a language by
himself clicking a button. That would be very simple as well, because all you
need to do is to change the language information class attribute on click.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
